Guide to the John B. Collins Papers, 1913-1976 AIS.1977.17
ULS Archives & Special Collections
John B. Collins Papers
1917-1976
1918-1935
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Collins, John B.
AIS.1977.17
2.5 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
Through the 1920s and 1930s, John B. Collins actively participated in various organizations and activities that supported establishment of an independent republic in Ireland. Additionally, Collins was also active in several organizations affiliated with the Catholic Church in Pittsburgh. The collection contains letters, publications, clippings, organizational records, memorabilia, handbills, pamphlets, posters, and photographs that Collins produced and collected as result of his concern with these subjects.
Biography
Long time Pittsburgh resident, John B. Collins actively participated in the city's Irish-Catholic community. A strong supporter of the struggle for an independent Irish Republic, Collins became an active member of the Pittsburgh chapters of the American Association for the Recognition of the Irish Republic (AARIR) and the Friends of Irish Freedom (FOIF) during the 1920s and 1930s. Both American based organizations worked to organize Irish-American support for the fight for Irish independence. A supporter of Eamon de Valera's pro-republican Fianna Fáil Party, Collins helped arrange the leader's 1927 and 1930 visits to Pittsburgh.
A member of Pittsburgh's Catholic community, Collins served as president of local chapters of the Holy Name Society and the Knights of Columbus and joined the Cecilian Society, the Catholic Society for Social Justice, and the Bishop's Club.
A man of strong political and religious conviction, and a prolific letter writer, Collins corresponded with people, organizations, and publications that he believed misrepresented the Irish cause or the beliefs and practices of the Roman Catholic Church.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection reflects John B. Collin's participation in the Irish Independence movement and various Catholic organizations in Pittsburgh from 1913 to 1976 and material he collected in relation to these interests.
The collection consists of five series. Series I contains material related to the organizations with which Collins affiliated and about which he collected material. Series II includes material dealing with Eamon de Valera, while Series III contains material regarding the 1935 controversy surrounding the showing of motion pictures on Sunday. Series IV consists of various correspondences and Series V contains miscellaneous material and memorabilia.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
On indefinite loan from the Irish Centre of Pittsburgh, 1977.
Previous Citation
John B. Collins Papers, 1913-1976, AIS.1977.17, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Irish Americans -- Pennsylvania -- History; Irish Americans -- Political activity; Irish Americans -- Societies and clubs; Allegheny County (Pa.); Personal papers; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Ethnic groups; Abbey Theatre; American Association for the Recognition of the Irish Republic; Catholic League for Social Justice; Catholic Church -- Societies, etc.; Cecilian Society; Collins, John B.; Cosgrave, William Thomas; De Valera, Eamonn; Friends of Irish Freedom; Holy Name Society; Irish Independence Club; Knights of Columbus; Kountz, Richard; Lynch, John M.; O'Mahoney, Joseph P.; Russell, Charles; Williams, Christopher H.
- Organizations, I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  The series contains correspondence, newspaper clippings, meeting minutes, constitutions, newsletters, pamphlets, programs, announcements, photographs, memorabilia, and publications pertaining to organizations to which either Collins belonged or about which he gathered material.
  - Abbey Theatre Company, 1931-1934 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - American Association for the Recognition of the Irish Republic, 1921-1932 (Box 1, Folder 5-11)
  - American Committee for Relief in Ireland (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - American Steel Foundries, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
  - Banban Brotherhood, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bishop's Club, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Catholic League for Social Justice, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
  - Cecilian Society, 1913-1924 (Box 1, Folder 21-24)
  - Friends of Irish Freedom, 1919-1921, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 25-32)
  - Holy Name Society, 1926-1932 (Box 2, Folder 1-16)
  - Irish Independence Club, 1931-1932 (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
  - Knights of Columbus, 1917-1930 (Box 2, Folder 19-23)
  - Laymen's Retreat Movement, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 1-5)
  - Little Sisters of the Poor, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 6-9)
  - National Council of Catholic Men Confernace, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 10-12)
- Eamon de Valera, II.
  The series focuses on material created and collected by Collins relating to the Irish Republican leader, Eamon de Valera. The series contains correspondence, newspaper clippings, meeting minutes, photographs, contracts, handbills, brochures, checks, invitation lists, and a publication. The bulk of the series concerns the arrangements for de Valera's 1927 and 1930 Pittsburgh visits and a banquet held to celebrate the 1932 election that placed de Valera at the head of the Irish Government as Taoiseach (priminister). Also included in these files are material concerning the development and American financial support of the Irish newspaper The Irish Press, Ltd. and a copy of de Valera's 1923 presidential address.
  - Copy of Presidential Message, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Minutes of Joint Meeting of Erskine childers and Padraic Pearse Councils (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Pittsburgh Visit, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
  - Pittsburgh Visit, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 17-22)
  - Irish Free Press, Ltd., 1929-1931 (Box 3, Folder 23-25)
  - Irish Presidential Election Results, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Pittsburgh Banquet Celebrating de Valera's Election, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 27-29)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Sunday Movie Controversy, III.
  The series contains five files concerning a 1935 attempt to change a Pennsylvania state law that forbade the showing of motion pictures on Sunday. The series reflects Collins' and the Church's attempts to encourage Pittsburgh's Catholic community to vote against a bill that would change the law.
  - Sunday Movie Controversy, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 31-35)
- Correspondence, IV.
  The series contains the correspondence of Collins on a wide range of topics. Additionally, material remains in the files that provide contextual information to the letters themselves. A large portion of the series consists of letters written by Collins to publications regarding the popular reference to William T. Cosgrave as the first president of the Irish Free State. Collins, like many other supporters of de Valera, believed that the treaty signed in 1921 forming the Irish Free State under the dominion of the English Crown was an unacceptable resolution of the struggle for Irish independence. Collins wrote letters regarding this subject to the Associated Press, several newspapers, and individuals. Other letters concern Collin's beliefs regarding contraception, Irish land annuities, the purchase of a car for Pittsburgh priest Father James Delaney, and various other issues. The files are arranged alphabetically.
  - America, Letters to the Editor, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Ave Maria, Letters to the Editor, 1931-1932 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Berchfield, Chris, letters from, 1922-1931 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Contraception, letter to the Pittsburgh Press and Related Clippings, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Cosgrave, William T., letters, related clippings, and pamphlets, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 3-5)
  - Delaney, Father James M., letters and clippings (Box 4, Folder 6-8)
  - Irish Land Annuities, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 9-11)
  - Irish Situation, correspondence with Associated Press re: dispatcher that appeared in the Pittsburgh Press, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Kuntz, Richard, 1923-1932 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - O'Mahoney, Joseph, Editor of The Indiana Catholic Reporter, letters and clippings, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 14-15)
  - Russell, Charles Edward, 1932-1933 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - St. Endas Church (Box 4, Folder 17-22)
  - St. Mary's Church (Box 4, Folder 23-25)
  - Williams, Christopher H., letters and article "Propoganda", 1923-1928 (Box 4, Folder 26-27)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, A-G, 1923-1927 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, H-O, 1923-1927 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, P-Z, 1923-1927 (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Miscellaneous, V.
  The series contains miscellaneous material collected by Collins. The material includes periodicals, pamphlets, essays and notes, broadsides, photographs, a map of the Irish Republic, press releases, and memorabilia. Most of the material is the product of publicizing the various Irish cultural events around Pittsburgh during the 1920's and 1930's.
  - Brian Boru Club, 1920 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Catholic Theater Bulletins, 1924, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Irish Centre of Pittsburgh, 1966, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Irish Faire (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Irish Freedom Fund (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Irish Martyrs (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Lynch, John, press release and transcripts of speech, 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 7-8)
  - Map of Irish Republic (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Meta Machine Company, annual report (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Saint Patrick's Day Charicatures, 1928-1931 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Sheet Music (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Statue of Westminster, Photograph (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Theater Programs (Box 5, Folder 14-19)
  - Theater Programs (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Ulster Delegation, copy of transcript, 1920 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Sinn Feiner, eight issues, 1921 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous Periodicals (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Pamphlets (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Essays (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Broadsides (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Unidentified Photograph (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Misc. Memorabilia (Box 5, Folder 28)